בוקר טוב *Boker Tov* everybody. Today's דף daf. *Daf* is דף טז
Daf Tes-Zayin. *Daf Tet-Zayin*. Happy ט"ו בשבט *Tu B'Shvat*, a little off,
טו *Tet-Vav*, טז *Tet-Zayin* in the דף *Daf* ט"ו בשבט *Tu B'Shvat*,
day one off. I don't know, by the way, if anybody saw
the blood moon this morning, but okay. I couldn't see anything. Okay,
really? You tried? Alright, anyway, so thanks to Michal yesterday for covering
the דף *Daf*. I wanted to highlight two important issues that came
up from yesterday's דף *Daf* and then we'll begin with today. Yesterday
was the whole issue, גמרא Gemara *Gemara* working through the specifics about
selling, you know, large animals, בהמה behemah גסה *Behemah Gassah*, whatever cows,
donkeys, horses to the non-Jew. And to
the concern basically a שבת Shabbos. *Shabbos* concern was the primary issue.
But תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot* once again asks the big question which is
what about our practice? That doesn't seem to be in line with
the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara*. And here you can't give the answer, oh
well, you know, we don't consider Christians עובדי עבודה זרה Avoda Zara,
*ovdei Avodah Zarah*. Because it has nothing to do with עבודה זרה
Avodah Zarah, *Avodah Zarah*. This has to do with the concern that
they're going to use it on שבת Shabbos. *Shabbos* and it'll only
be rented or borrowed and it'll be a problem of our animals
doing work on שבת Shabbos *Shabbos*. So תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot* has to
deal with it. Now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* did say, had a
discussion about if you sell a cow then
it's okay to sell a cow because you can assume they're going
to slaughter it and they're not going to work it. But then
תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot*'s question was, okay is an ox included in this
or do we assume they definitely will use an ox as a
beast of labor? So he has a whole interesting question about oxen
versus cow. But even if you say that it's permissible to sell
cow and ox, that still remains, it's forbidden to sell, the משנה
Mishna *Mishnah* says it's forbidden to sell, you know, young cattle, young
horses, and horses is forbidden. And תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot* says our practice
is to sell all this stuff. So what's the story? So if
you take a look at תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot* on טו עמוד א
*Tet-Vav Amud Alef*, the big תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot*, if you look at
the bottom, he says like
this. He
says וגם *VeGam*, we'll start
with that. He says וגם לפעמים שעובד כוכבים kochavim מפרש שקונה בשביל
מלאכת חרישה משיכת קרון *VeGam lifamim
she'oved kochavim
mefaresh shekoneh bishvil melachat charisha meshichat karon*. He says sometimes
they're explicit and they're saying they're going to buy it for plowing,
they're going to buy it for carrying the wagon. So anyway, why
do all these prohibitions not apply? Why do we go ahead even
for something like cows and oxen for a minute, why do we
sell them, horses, donkeys, the whole thing? He says ויש לומר Ve-yesh
lomar *Ve-yesh lomar*,
you can say, דלפי מסקנת התלמוד דשרי למכור אידי דתפסירא *de-lefi maskanat
ha-Talmud de-shari limkor idi de-tafsira* that you can sell through a middleman,
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* allowed. ומפרש טעמא משום דלא ידעי ליה לקליה
*U-mefaresh ta'ama mishum de-lo yada leh lekalah*. Oh, why can you sell
through a middleman? Because it won't do מלאכה melacha *melacha* on שבת
Shabbos *Shabbos*, because it won't know your voice. He says ניחא דגם
בהמה behema, שלנו אינה מכירה בקולנו *nicha de-gam behemah shelanu einah makirah
bekoleinu*. Oh, there's many ירידת הדורות *Yeridat Hadorot* even when it comes
to the animals, okay, so animals nowadays don't recognize our voices. So
therefore there's not the concern that we'll speak and it'll cause the
animal to come here to do it on שבת Shabbos *Shabbos*. Of
course the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says that's only when you're selling them,
but how about concerns about renting and lending, right, which the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* said you know we would rule that that would be
a problem of your animal if it's rented or lent on שבת
Shabbos *Shabbos*. וגם לא lo, שכיח לנו להשאיל ולהשכיר *Ve-gam lo shechiach
lanu le-hash'il u-le-haskir*. And we can also throw in that we normally
don't rent and lend them, so maybe
technically... alright, he's going to get there. מיהו *Mihu*. So that would
solve it if we could say technically we're not dealing with animals
that we normally rent and lend and there's no concern that they'll
say come here and so on. But then he says מיהו מאותם
שרגילים לשכור לעובדי כוכבים קשיא kashya. *Mihu me-otam she-regilim liskor le-ovdei kochavim
kasha*. But the animals that we normally do rent to non-Jews, how
are we allowed to do this? Why are we not concerned that
it'll be rented on שבת Shabbos. *Shabbos*, that even to sell it,
the selling if we allow selling it'll lead to renting. ויש לומר
דודאי הא דאסר למכור בהמה טמאה היינו דוקא בימיהם *Ve-yesh lomar de-vadai
had de-asar limkor behemah tmeiah hayne davka
bi-ymeihem*. Listen to this, now it's not just a question about oh
they're not עובדי עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah. *ovdei Avodah Zarah*. He actually
gives a sort of socioeconomic way in which, which recognizes his different
socioeconomic reality and why this type of a הלכה halacha *halakha* is
not sustainable in the life in which he lives.
That they prohibited those types of sales was דוקא בימיהם *davka bi-ymeihem*.
שהיו הרבה יהודים ביחד *She-hayu harbeh Yehudim beyachad*. There were
they had these tight clusters of Jewish communities particularly I would add
in the land of Israel which is where this was said. ואם
היו לאדם בהמה שאינו צריך לה היה מוכר לחברו *Ve-im hayu le-adam
behemah she-eino tzarich lah haya mocher
le-chaveiro*. So you know you had other alternatives if we said don't
sell it to the non-Jew. You could sell it to your friend
a Jew, okay, and maybe you can even do business, you have
a big enough Jewish community you could do business by just turning
around and selling amongst within the Jewish community. ולא היה מפסיד *Velo
haya mafsid*, you wouldn't have to lose the animal. אבל aval עתה
מה יעשה שלא ימצא למכור יפסיד *Aval ata mah ya'aseh she-lo yimtzah
limkor yafsid*.
So nowadays he says, if you buy a horse and now you
no longer need the horse, you have an extra horse, you have
an extra cow, he says, if there's ten Jews living in the
community and so what are you gonna do? חזל Chazal never would
have wanted us to have to waste the animal. Okay, that's what
תוספות Tosafos says. He's acknowledging that his reality is that they do
not keep to this. And probably תוספות Tosafos is 100% correct that
it was the economic reasons that made it impossible to keep to
this. So תוספות Tosafos is actually acknowledging that. And then what he's
doing is he is retroprojecting that and saying, and we can assume
that the rabbis only meant this תקנה takkana when it would not
create economic hardship. But in our reality where it does not where
we don't have any alternatives and it creates economic hardship, they would
not allow it. Sort of like if you remember what רשי Rashi
says, why does גמרא Gemara say that like outside of Israel you
can do business before their before the holiday? I'm like, we gotta
do business, gotta make a living, and that basically winds up being
the reason תוספות Tosafos says that you can even wind up doing
business like for one explanation on their holiday. Like to a certain
degree they only meant this in a case where it was sustainable.
In our society, תוספות Tosafos says this is not sustainable. ולכך נהגו
הגאונים שבגולה, ul'kach nahagu hagaonim shebagola,
and therefore תוספות Tosafos says this already goes back to the גאונים.
Geonim. Now does he mean technically the גאונים? Geonim? Does he mean
the earlier authorities? Anyway, היתר בדבר, hetter badavar, to they
practice that it was okay in our economic reality we have to
allow it. וכי האי גוונא איכא למימר דאפילו הכי תוסר נמי נסתבין
משום הכי אם אפשר הכי נמי אבל כיון דאי אפשר שרי. v'chi
hay gvna ika l'meimar d'afilu hachi tivsar nami nistabin mishani im efshar
hachi nami aval kivan d'i efshar shari.
Fine. Then he says, so basically there's an economic reality. But then
he says, ופסק רבינו ברוך דלפי זה, upasak Rabbeinu Baruch d'lfi zeh,
if the only allowance is is that it's not sustainable and we're
not gonna ask you to waste your animal if you have no
use for it and there's no Jews around who want to buy
it, אין להתיר אלא כשקונה סוס לצורך עצמו ונמלך עליו למוכרו, ein
l'hattir ela k'shekonneh sus l'tzorech atzmo v'nimlach alav l'mochro,
that's only if you get stuck in that situation. You bought a
horse and then you have and then you don't need it anymore.
Okay, דאם לא ימכרנו יפסיד. d'im lo yachreni yafsid. But see
what they need was Craigslist. אבל לוקח סוסים למוכרם כדי להרויח אסור.
aval lokeach susim l'mochram kedei l'harviach assur. But if you're doing it
for a business, who says you have to go into that business?
Okay, דלא יכרם ולא יפסיד להם. d'lo yichreh v'lo yafsid lahem.
It's one thing to say you don't have to if you have
an extra horse, you don't have you know it's you know we
didn't make you sort of throw it out whatever we didn't make
you like just lose your investment, okay. We know a lot of
times חזל Chazal allowed certain things because of a דבר האבד. davar
ha'avad. Okay, it doesn't mean we allow you to go into business
for that reason. Okay, but bottom line, of course, they were going
into business for that reason. All right, and they and anyway, and
once again, תוספות Tosafos sort of implicitly this תוספות Tosafos was powerful
because he acknowledges that the reason why they're doing it is the
economics realities like Jews do not have the ability, also think about
it this way. As I said, you know, in when this was
sort of said, a lot of this was said in the land
of Israel where the Jews were able to do agriculture, right? You
know, when the Jews in the Middle Ages could not, you know,
they weren't allowed to own land and do agriculture. So first of
all, their types of economic, you know,
reality where opportunities were more limited. Second of all, as I said,
I think the subtext of all of this, which isn't being said
in the גמרא, Gemara is that all these things we're doing right
now were fundamentally focused about the land of Israel to increase Jewish
presence in the land of Israel and to strengthen like, you know,
the Jewish society, so you're not sort of selling away your assets
outside of the community. And so תוספות Tosafot is right because you
already have a certain size community that you want to strengthen and
further establish. Okay, and תוספות Tosafot, acknowledges that the economic and societal
realities were different and that led to people this not being sustainable.
People had to find פרנסה parnassa and people went ahead and did
it. And then he's just trying to use that to say, well,
we can assume that חזל would never have meant to apply this
תקנה takkana in cases where it would have led, you know, to
such types of hardship. So it's a really interesting תוספות Tosafot as
a window into sort of those realities. Yes. So I'm trying to
just put it all together. I mean, at some point we brought
up the bestiality part, so where'd all that go? Was that only
a מנהג? minhag? And that was a place to place and where
they were where that חשש chashash was present and so on. So
so basically saying they're not really חושד choshed at all? Right. Well,
right. Okay, except in other we'll get to another case when it's
your animal in an inn, but but for selling animals we're not
חושד. choshed. Right, but but doesn't that doesn't solve a going to
the hotel and then you know, hooray whatever I'm here. What if
you would say דזמננו, d'zmanenu, they're not חושד choshed על כך al
kach whatever? Okay, I'm sure he could come up with some answer.
Yes. And the other question I had was in terms of if
we were so not worried if there if it can be תולה
toleh like okay, he wants to have the cow for שחיטה, shechita,
right? Then why wasn't that in our משנה Mishna at all? Or
משנה Mishna didn't say. So תוספות Tosafot, deals with that, okay? I
don't want to get into the specifics. תוספות Tosafot tries to figure
out how come how come our משנה Mishna seems to not acknowledge
that.
Yeah, משנה Mishnah is more concerned with the בהמה דקה behema daka
and the other... Yeah. Right. Right. Right. Okay, right. And also we
did talk about עבודה זרה, Avodah Zarah I think, in detail.
Right, right, right. Exactly. Okay, right. Okay, I want to make one
other quick point. So it's always fascinating I think when they're dealing
with the gap between what the גמרא Gemara is saying or what
their practice reality is as a and then you sort of see
how they use halakhic strategies, but this תוספות Tosafot, in particular, acknowledging
the socio-economic reality. The other one is an interesting halakhic point because
I think I had a beautiful diagram here about לפני עור lifnei
iver and maybe... and maybe Michal made this point already, but if
you remember, the גמרא Gemara started to discuss, you can't sell these
types of animals to another Jew if you're concerned that that Jew
will go ahead and then sell it to a non-Jew. And then
it dealt with כותים, Kutim, showing you can't sell to כותים Kutim
because a כותי Kuti will sell to a non-Jew. So תוספות Tosafot
asks the question, what do you mean? The other day we said
on דף י"ד Daf Yod Dalet that לפני עור Lifnei Iver was
forbidden, לפני דלפני, Lifnei de-Lifnei, two degrees removed, was permissible. So take
a look at this short תוספות, Tosafot bottom of דף ט"ו עמוד
ב', Daf Tet Vav Amud Bet, ואובדי כוכבים מזבין ליה, U've-ovdei kochavim
mazbin lei, תוספות Tosafot says לישראל לא מזבין ליה. Le-Yisrael lo mazbin
lei. Okay, ובמסקנא U've-maskana לישראל מסקינן le-Yisrael maskinan דאסור למיזבן לישראל חשוד,
de-assur le-mizban le-Yisrael chashud,
you can't sell it to a Jew who is suspect for selling
to non-Jews because then that Jew is going to transgress selling these
animals. ומאי שנא מלפני דלפני דלעיל, U'mai shna mi-lifnei de-lifnei de-le'eil,
but before we permit לפני דלפני? Lifnei de-Lifnei? And if you think
about it here, even if the Jew sells to non-Jews, maximum what?
He transgresses a rabbinic prohibition of selling animals to non-Jews. There we
were talking about like selling incense that was going to be burnt
to עבודה זרה, avoda zara that was permissible two degrees removed. ויש
לומר says תוספות, Tosafot דהתם מאי באובדי כוכבים, De-hasam mai be-ovdei kochavim,
I mentioned this to you when we learned it at the time,
שאינו מוזהר על לפני עור. She-eino muzhar al lifnei iver. לפיכך איננו
חוששים באובדי כוכבים אם יתנם לחברו. Le-fichach einanu chosheshim be-ovdei kochavim im
yitnem le-chavero.
When I sell to non-Jew number one, that non-Jew is not prohibited
on לפני עור. Lifnei Iver. So I haven't been מכשיל, machshil, right,
I haven't caused non-Jew number one to sin. He's not going to
burn it for incense and I haven't caused him to sin because
he'll transgress לפני עור Lifnei Iver because non-Jews are not prohibited in
לפני עור. Lifnei Iver. So I haven't caused that non-Jew to sin
at all. And the non-Jew number two is not my, is not
me, is not my connection. My only connection is to non-Jew number
one. But if I sell to a Jew who is going to
sell this animal to a non-Jew, okay,
so I might not, so let's let's see what he says, אבל
he says, אינו חושש מעובדי כוכבים אם יתנם לחברו. eino choshesh me-ovdei
kochavim im yitnem le-chavero. אבל הכא דמאי בישראל החשוד, Aval hacha de-mai
be-Yisrael ha-chashud, I'm going to sell to a Jew who then transgresses
the rabbinic prohibition and sell to a non-Jew, אנו מצווים שלא יבוא
שום ישראל לידי תקלה על ידינו. Anu metzuvim she-lo yavo shum Yisrael
lidei takala al yadeinu.
First of all, תוספות Tosafot says our responsibility to our fellow Jew
goes, you know, it goes beyond technical לפני עור. Lifnei Iver. There's
a very powerful point. Okay. If I sell to Michael and then
Michael goes ahead and sells to, well actually, you know, yeah, Michael
goes ahead and sells to like a non-Jew. My responsibility, first of
all, says תוספות, Tosafot you know, is that, is that... well let's
see how to read it. I, even
if it's, well let me sort of pull back and give this
type of an example. Remember the גמרא Gemara says that לפני עור
Lifnei Iver is only תרי עברי דנהרא trei avri de-nahara if the
guy can't get it himself. But if the guy can get it
himself, it's not לפני עור. Lifnei Iver. So does that really mean
it's מותר? muttar? Michael comes along to me and there's his and
here's Michael's נבילה neveilah sitting right here, okay, and I know Michael
is, or cheeseburger, and I know Michael's weakness, cheeseburgers, whatever, it's his
cheeseburger, it's sitting right here, and he says, Dov, would you mind
handing that to me? And I say, oh, well, he could pick
it up himself, it's not לפני עור, Lifnei Iver, it's not תרי
עברי דנהרא, trei avri de-nahara, sure Michael, here it is. Okay, so
most of the ראשונים Rishonim say no, חס ושלום, chas veshalom, I
can't do that. Even if it's not technical לפני עור, Lifnei Iver,
I can't do anything that could somehow help a fellow Jew do
an עבירה, aveira, even if it's not לפני עור. Lifnei Iver. And
they frame it different ways: לפני עור דרבנן, Lifnei Iver de-Rabbanan, מכשיל,
machshil, other types of things. But let's say, let's say it was
my friend Christopher, okay, and he was asking for some some אבר
מן החי, ever min hachai, and he says, and it's his אבר
מן החי, ever min hachai, and he says, Dov, would you mind
handing the אבר מן החי? ever min hachai? And I would say,
sure, no problem, here it is. That actually might be מותר. muttar.
Since it's not technical לפני עור, Lifnei Iver, okay, my responsibility towards
non-Jews in terms of their שמירת מצוות, shmirat mitzvot, one way of
framing it... Wait, why is it not לפני עור? Lifnei Iver? Because
he could pick it up himself. It's not תרי עברי דנהרא. trei
avri de-nahara. So here's a way of framing it. Okay. By Jews,
I have an active responsibility to be concerned that Jews don't sin.
It's not just that I can't actively aid and abet them. I
have actively concerned to try to get as many Jews to be
שומרי מצוות shomrei mitzvot as possible. Okay, so therefore, even if it's
not לפני עור, Lifnei Iver, I can't do something that's leading him
to sin. For a non-Jew, as long as I'm not directly being
מכשיל machshil him, it's okay. So תוספות says, so when, so getting
back to to me giving it to Michael and Michael's going to
sell it to a non-Jew, it might not be לפני עור Lifnei
Iver because it might be two degrees removed from the transgression, okay,
but nevertheless, I have a higher responsibility to my fellow Jew and
I have a higher responsibility to make sure even though I'm not
directly sort of cause doing the sin, I'm one degree removed, I
have a greater responsibility to make sure that Michael here doesn't sin.
Number one. And number two, and this the second answer is even
simpler just sort of in a formal way. He says,
ורב אשי ועוד דחד לפני הוא, v'Rav Ashi v'od d'chad lifnei hu,
שלא יחטא ישראל בשאלה ושכירה מנסיוני. she-lo yechete Yisrael bi-she'ela u-sechira mi-nisyonei.
It's what I said before. If I am
being עובר over on a לפני עור, lifnei iver, not on the,
you know, I'm my concern is, Michael is definitely going to now
transgress the rabbinic prohibition. I'm concerned that by selling it to Michael,
I'm מכשיל machshil Michael directly in the rabbinic prohibition. Okay, so anyway,
the bottom line is, I don't know if you, whatever, I don't
know if I fully explained or if I was as clear as
I could be, but the basic point is, is that לפני דלפני
lifnei de'lifnei is okay by a non-Jew because if you sell it
to a non-Jew, you're not directly causing the second non-Jew to sin
and the first non-Jew is not prohibited in לפני עיוור. Lifnei Iver.
But if you sell it to a Jew and the Jew is
then going to sell it to either another Jew or a non-Jew
etc, then I am being עובר over on לפני עיוור Lifnei Iver
of the Jew I'm interacting with, his transgression that he's going to
now violate the rabbinic prohibition or his transgression that because he'll sell
it, he'll be עובר over on the איסור issur of using his
בהמה on שבת. Shabbos. And my responsibility to Michael is so great
that I have to be more concerned either A because Michael's prohibited
in לפני עיוור, Lifnei Iver, so I have that, and also my
general responsibility to Jews is more of an active one than just
a don't violate type of a one. And this question on י"ד
Yud Daled with עבודה זרה. avoda zara When you're selling it to
a non-Jew, but if you're selling it to this object whose only
use could possibly be עבודה זרה avoda zara. in the end. Right.
But that's not my responsibility. As long as I do not, I'm
not directly involved in the non-Jew's sin. It's a bit of a
fiction. It's not a fiction, it's just a question about how far
does my responsibility lie. By my fellow Jews I'm actively responsible to
try to get them to be as שומר מצוות shomer mitzvos as
possible. I mean we're not going to deal now with the whole
sort of, you know, modern-day like whatever, pluralism etc, okay, but in
general I'm concerned with the שמירת מצוות, shmiras mitzvos, I'm actively concerned
with the שמירת מצוות shmiras mitzvos of Jews. Okay, so if it's
going to lead to some Jew sinning, that should be a problem
for me. Whereas by non-Jews, it's just I can't be actively involved
in the עבירה, aveira, okay? So it's not a fiction, sure they'll
do it, but that's not, I'm not directly involved and the other
start is plus isn't my responsibility. Okay? My so, alright. Yes. Go
ahead. Well one person who would be trying to express on that,
ah okay, because the כוכבים are for the עובד כוכבים oved kochavim
and then for the ישראל. Yisrael.
That's cute. A lot of concern for the Jew, but can he
sell to the non-Jew that it's פשוט pashut and then... Very good.
But there is a Punder-zo, it's like a... Yeah I know what
it is, yeah. So they have one on a secular Israeli asking
directions. Oh that's hilarious, that's hilarious. Okay. Right. Right. Exactly.
I know, I know.
It's pretty hilarious. It goes
like: 'Wai-wai'. Yeah, yeah, it's like it's like 'So where is this,
so it's if somebody wanted to go they would go west'. So
it's whatever, it's this hilarious thing. This secular Israeli is driving a
car on שבת. Shabbos, Secular Israeli is driving a car on שבת
Shabbos, and he pulls in front of this פרום frum guy coming
home from שול shul and he says like 'Oh, excuse me, can
you tell me how to get to like רחוב דיזנגוף?' Rehov Dizengoff?
So he says 'Well, if somebody were going to רחוב דיזנגוף, Rehov
Dizengoff, they would be heading west.' He says 'Well, what are you
saying, which west?' He says 'Oh look, I forgot my כיפה, kippah,
oh look it's so west!'
It goes around, like you can do a whole
פשט peshat about like לפני עיוור. Lifnei Iver. It's a brilliant piece.
Anyway. Alright, so with that said, now we actually have to get
to today's דף. So let's turn to דף ט"ז. We pick up
where אמר רב אדא. Amar Rav Adda. Okay, it's like six lines
from the top. אמר רב אדא בר אהבה: Amar Rav Adda bar
Ahava: אין מוכרין להן אשישיות של ברזל. Ein mocherin lahen ashisheiot shel
barzel. You cannot sell them like iron ignots to non-Jews because you're
afraid they're going to melt it down and use it for
weapons, okay? מאי טעמא? Mai ta'ama? משום דחלשינה מנייהו Mishum de'chalshina minnaihu
כלי זין, klei zayin, weapons. אי הכי אפילו מריי וחציני נמי? I-haki
afilu marrei ve'chatzini nami? If that's true, you shouldn't even be able
to sell them like spades and pickaxes because they'll melt it down
and turn it into weapons. So the obvious point is like you
don't assume somebody's going to ruin a nice כלי, kli, a nice,
you know, spade just to make a weapon. But you know, iron
ignots are specifically going to be turned into something. Anyway the גמרא
Gemara says: כלי
זין? klei zayin? אי הכי זו נמי? I-haki zo nami? So אמר
רב זביד: Amar Rav Zvid: בפרזלא הינדואה. Be-parzela Hindua. No, we're only
talking about Indian iron, which is very like strong and good for
weapon use.
ואידנא דקא מזבנינא? Ve-idna de-ka mezabnina? So why now do we sell
them Indian iron? אמר רב אשי: Amar Rav Ashi: לפרסאי. Le-Parsai. We
only sell it to Persians, דמגנו עלן. de-magenu alan. So here's again
a certain reality that is different. They were dealing not with the
Romans, they were dealing with the Persians, and the Persians were a
very, you know,
welcoming host country that cared about their Jewish population and they actually,
now they might go ahead and use these weapons in war, but
that's seen as protect us. You know, that's always the question, which
side are you on, right? The, you know, if it's your side
then using it in war to fight against people is good because
it's protecting you. If you're the other side then it's terrible because
you're killing our people off. Okay so anyway, so that was seen
as actually, you know, the realities were different.
Okay, עגלים וסיחים. agalim ve-siachim. Now you cannot sell even young animals,
but because like young calves and foals. תניא Tanya רבי יהודה מתיר
בשבורה, Rabbi Yehuda matir bi-shvura, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda allows if it
has a, you know, the משנה Mishnah. says whether it has a,
whether it's full or broken, but the ברייתא Braita says that רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda actually says if it's got a broken leg it's
not a problem. מפני שאינה יכולה להתרפאות לחיות mipnei she-eina yechola l'hitrapos
l'achiyos because it's, you can't heal and it can't and it's gonna
die, so you can go ahead and sell it. You know, maybe
the non-Jew will turn it into meat but you don't have to
worry that it's gonna be around.
Now, now presumably we're gonna assume like the גמרא Gemara assumes, I
want to just remind you that this whole שבת Shabbos, explanation is
not in the משנה. Mishnah It's all the גמרא Gemara inserted it.
I still think that it's something else, okay, I still think it
has to do with presence in the land of Israel. But anyway,
but רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says either way, if the animal's gonna
die and be שחט, shechted, it's not gonna be used as a
beast of burden or some type of agricultural thing. No שבת Shabbos.
concerns, no other concerns, go ahead and sell it. So אמרו לו,
amru lo, they said to him, ולא מרבינה לה ליולדות? v'lo marbeena
lah l'yoledess? No, because if it's a female one, they can use
it to have, you know, bring other animals on top of it
to copulate and it'll give birth to kids and therefore it'll still
be a problem. Now, why is that a problem? I mean, from
my explanation, okay, it's a problem, it'll still help them in terms
of creating having more animals. But if it's the שבת Shabbos issue,
how do you explain big deal? This animal still isn't gonna work
on שבת. Shabbos. So רש״י Rashi says it's like a מראית עין
maris ayin concern. Since they're not gonna שחט shecht the animal right
away and they're gonna leave it in their house, so in order
to produce more baby animals, baby cows or baby horses or whatever
it is, so therefore people will see it in the house and
assume you sold it to the non-Jew when it wasn't a broken
leg. And therefore that will lead to you, to other people selling
animals to non-Jews that don't have broken legs, which seems a little
bit far-fetched because like the whole thing is only a rabbinic restriction,
we normally aren't so concerned about safeguarding rabbinic restrictions. Even the rabbinic
restriction is only a safeguard to, you know, you can't sell it
because you might come to rent it, or you can't sell it
because you might come to it ערב שבת erev Shabbos and might
use it, you know, before the sale was final, come to, come
to do it, you know, have it, you know, have it move
because of you. It seems pretty extreme that we would be concerned
about מראית עין maris ayin around these issues. Okay. A horse with
a broken leg's not gonna heal? Yeah. Yeah, the assumption is it's
not gonna. A horse with a broken leg is not gonna heal.
You know, you know those stories, the horse breaks a leg, they
take it out, they shoot it? Right, that's right. That's why I'm
not understanding the, meaning they're saying it'll heal and people will see
it and think that. No,
it won't heal. You'll leave it around with the broken leg to
produce in order to get pregnant and produce babies. And then? And
people will assume, oh, what's that non-Jew doing with חיים Chaim's horse?
It must be that חיים Chaim sold it to him and then
it broke the leg. And you'll assume, they won't even,
they'll be חושד choshed that you know even what they're not seeing,
oh, he must've, he must've violated. Oh, חיים Chaim can violate. You
know, it seems so far-fetched, you know? Anyway, okay, וכיון דמרבינה לה
ליולדות אתי לשהוייה, v'cheivan d'marbeena lah l'yoledess, asi l'shahuye, it'll come to
leave it around.
אמר להם לכשתלד, amar lahem, lich'shetayled, so רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda said
back to them, I'll worry about it when it gives birth. Okay,
אלמא, alma, which means big deal. Okay, but the גמרא Gemara says
it actually means he's not concerned that they'll do it. לא מקבל
הזכר. lo mikabel ha-zachar. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda's claim is is that
actually an animal once it's got a broken leg isn't in the
mood and will not be interested, I don't know if that's true,
anyway, will not be interested in being able and being receptive to.
No, we're not, we're not concerned about it here, who, I don't
know where you started bringing that in. Okay, אינה יכולה להתרפאות, eina
yechola l'hitrapos, they did not challenge the אינה יכולה להתרפאות. eina yechola
l'hitrapos. They said even if it can't heal, they're gonna leave it
around to use it. And רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda said they're not
gonna leave it around to use it. They're just gonna shoot it,
be done with it. Okay. בן בתירה מתיר בסוס. Ben Bethera matir
b'sus. Now בן בתירה Ben Bethera allows a horse. Okay, now why?
What's the issue with a horse? So תניא בן בתירה מתיר בסוס
מפני שהוא עושה בו מלאכה שאין חייבין עליה חטאת. Tanya Ben Bethera
matir b'sus mipnei she-hu oseh bo melacha she-ein chayavin aleha chatas. So
this ברייתא Braita of בן בתירה Ben Bethera is the one time
it's explicit that at least for בן בתירה Ben Bethera it's about
מלאכה melacha on שבת. Shabbos. And therefore בן בתירה Ben Bethera says
since for me it's about מלאכה melacha on שבת, Shabbos since a
horse is used for riding on, so even if I rode on
my horse on שבת, Shabbos I would not violate a biblical prohibition
of using my animal to do מלאכה melacha. on שבת, Shabbos right,
because it is because because because it's not carrying, it's only if
the animal does מלאכה. melacha Even though it's carrying me, since the
principle is חי נושא את עצמו, chai nosei es atzmo, like I
you know I sort of support my own weight, therefore it's very
true by the way, once a person is dead you know they
say dead weight, it really is true the diff, anyway, since I
support my own weight, technically it is not a violation if a
person would carry me, a biblical violation, it's not a biblical violation
if a horse carries me. So בן בתירה Ben Bethera said so
you can sell it, even if it'll lead to renting and other
things, at most it'll only lead to a rabbinic violation, not a
horse doing a biblical violation. So for him it's clearly about שבת.
Shabbos, Okay. ורבי אוסר מפני שני דברים. v'Rebbi oser mipnei shnei devarim.
And רבי Rebbi prohibits
for two reasons. אחד משום תורת כלי זיין, echad mishum toras klei
zayin,
because they could use horses as a type of a weapon, you
know, they go they use these horses in war and we'll see
about that in a minute. So that gets to the prohibition of
selling non-Jews things that are used for weapons. ואחד משום תורת בהמה
גסה. v'echad mishum toras behema gassa.
And number two it's prohibited just because it's a large animal and
the rabbis forbade large animals. Of course that's a little bit circular
because we're... why they forbade large animals and what category this falls
in. So let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. בשלמא תורת כלי
זיין איכא דכתבי בסחופיה. bishlama torat klei zayin ika dekativi besichufei.
I understand as a type of a weapon because there's some horses
that will kill people by trampling on them and they'll be used
directly in war, which is interesting. It sounds like if it was
only used indirectly, like can I sell them army jeeps? Right? Something
that itself is not used to inflict violence, but it's part of
the war effort. Why didn't the גמרא Gemara just say you ride
into battle in a horse? Okay, it sounds like the only prohibition
is if the thing itself is a weapon. Okay, it's not anything
related to war, it's weapons. But the horse sometimes will be a
weapon. Okay, אלא תורת בהמה גסה מאי? ella torat behema gassa mai?
But what do you mean it's a, it's in the prohibition of
large animals? His whole point is that it's not a
שבת problem. So אמר רבי יוחנן amar Rabbi Yochanan לכשיזקין מטחינו בריחיים
בשבת. lechsheyazkin matchino bereichayim beShabbos. No, you can wind up using it
on שבת. Once this horse gets old, you stop using it for
riding and you put it to turn the millstone and therefore there
are cases where it will do מלאכה melacha. on שבת. Of course
the funny, funny thing is but when I'm selling it, it's not
old, it's young. You know, so again, the question is oh, but
you know people will see it after it's been in the גוי's
goy hands 20 years, you know, it's like a type of a
מראית העין marit ha'ayin and then they'll think you sold it when
it was old. It becomes these very like very far-fetched types of
things. An easier way to explain this is, you know when the
גמרא Gemara says the language תורת כלי זיין torat klei zayin there's
always this principle of like לא פלוג. lo plug. Right? לא פלוג
lo plug is we do not like making these subdivisions. Like if
it's forbidden we're going to forbid the whole category. We're not going
to start worrying if it exactly applies to the specifics of this
category. That's like what the משנה Mishnah says. Sounds like. The משנה
mishna. says I don't care if it's old or if it's young,
if it's whole or if it's broken. We just forbid the whole
category. Now that would all be nice, but then the גמרא Gemara
seems to work under that when the גמרא Gemara starts talking about
allowing you to sell cows, you know, because of this circumstance and
other types of exceptions. Okay, but one way of understanding the response
of תורת בהמה גסה torat behema gassa just means don't bother me
about the details. We just forbid the whole category. But anyway, the
גמרא Gemara says there actually are cases in which it will be
a problem. All right. So maybe because the גמרא Gemara is bothered
like why it's one thing to say ninety percent of horses are
a problem and therefore we're going to extend it to the other
ten percent even when it gets a broken leg. But what רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is saying is no horses are a problem, there's
never a שבת issue. So what the גמרא's Gemara saying is well
sometimes a horse is a problem and therefore we forbid the whole
category. Interesting question, you know, in terms of like the weapons, something
that,
meaning like a sword, you can kill with the sword. But if
I sell a gun, well without the bullets it's nothing. Well, when
it's used, it's used as a weapon, that's different, that's different. Anyway,
the גמרא Gemara says like this, אסור. asur. או דלמא, o dilma,
I'm sorry, so now the גמרא Gemara has like this, the following
question. So אמר רבי יוחנן הלכה כבן בתירא. amar Rabbi Yochanan halacha
keBen Beteira.
Now we rule like בן בתירא, Ben Beteira, which is nice. And
that's consistent with the earlier גמרא Gemara about allowing to sell a
cow. Because this means we're not going to take a total לא
פלוג lo plug approach. We're actually going to ask is this particular
case a problem. And that actually gives you a lot more latitude.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara wants to know the following question.
איבעיא להו. iba'aya lehu. Okay, so that was about the horse. Now
שור, shor, so and that was a particular שבת argument like horses
are not going to be a שבת problem. Now איבעיא להו iba'aya
lehu that's a question. שור של פטם מהו? shor shel patam mahu?
What if you have a fattened ox? Or fattened cow? Things that
are specifically, you know, fat and done this way because their whole
purpose is to be used to slaughter and to make meat. Interesting
debate in תוספות whether it means that this is the type of
species but it hasn't been fattened yet or it's already been fattened.
Okay, but anyway you got a fattened cow, what's the story? Well
let's take a look. Okay, איבעיא להו שור של פטם מהו? iba'aya
lehu shor shel patam mahu? תיבעי לרבי יהודה תיבעי לרבנן. tibei leRabbi
Yehuda tibei leRabbanan. You could ask according to רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
you could ask according to the רבנן. Rabbanan. תיבעי לרבי יהודה tibei
leRabbi Yehuda who allows with a broken leg, עד כאן לא שרא
רבי יהודה אלא בשבורה ad kan lo shara Rabbi Yehuda ella beshvura
a broken leg, דלא חזיא למלאכה delo chazya limlacha such type of
an animal will never be fit for work, and therefore he makes
an exception, אבל האי דכי משהי ליה אתי לכלל מלאכה aval hai
dechi mashhei lei atei lichlal melacha but this type of an animal
you could leave it around and eventually it'll be fit for work.
So maybe it's enough in the category. This is a type of
a לא פלוג lo plug question. Again, רש"י Rashi reads this whole
thing about מראית העין marit ha'ayin I don't want to get into
רש"י. Rashi. But it's a type of a לא פלוג lo plug
thing. You know, on the one hand רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says
look it's got a broken leg so he's willing to make subdivisions
within a category, so make subdivisions here. But they say wait, there's
still a difference. That's a type of a category that yes it's
an exception and we don't like to make exceptions but that's an
exception that now it's fully out of the category. This type of
a case it's not fully out, you can always, it can always
eventually be fit for מלאכה. melacha. Okay, אסור. asur. That's one type
of perspective, maybe even רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda would say it's אסור.
asur. או דלמא אפילו לרבנן, o dilma afilu leRabbanan, even to the
Rabbis who don't allow the broken leg, לא קאסרי התם אלא דסתמא
לאו לשחיטה קאי lo kaasri hatam ella destama lav lishchita kai because
they'll say that something with a broken leg, their claim was you're
not going to שחט shecht it, you're going to use it for
making baby animals. Okay, and maybe also they would say a broken
leg is not like a category of animals, so that's a לא
פלוג, lo plug, it's fundamentally a horse and a horse is or
a cow and a cow is forbidden. אבל הא דסתמא לשחיטה קאי
aval ha destama lishchita kai this is a different category. Number one,
as So maybe therefore they should allow this. אפילו רבנן שרו, Afilu
rabbanan sharu, maybe even the rabbis would allow it. תא שמע, Ta
shema, come and hear. דאמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל D'amar Rav Yehuda
amar Shmuel של בית רבי היו מקריבין שור של פטם ביום אידם.
Shel Beit Rabbi hayu makrivin shor shel patem b'yom idam. In Rabbi,
you know Rabbi was the נשיא, Nasi, he had to be on
good relations with the Roman government, so actually, although we just said
about all the business is forbidden to give them on the day
of their holiday, Rabbi was required, you know, as an or not
expected, you know, felt it was in their good interest so to
the Jewish community on the Roman holiday to send them a nice
fattened calf. Okay, so first of all, the irony is he's not
just סתם stam doing business. Wait, for הקרבה. hakrava. For הקרבה. hakrava.
He's not just סתם stam doing business, right, he's actually giving something
specifically in honor of their holiday. And also the phrase used היה
מקריב haya makriv is powerful. הגמרא Gemara has this elsewhere as well.
It sort of means give as a tribute, you know, as a
tribute. So now Michael could be right, it also means that what
they're going to do with it is use it as a sacrifice,
and that might also be implied by the word מקריב, makriv, but
it also frames the very giving as a type of a sacrifice
and a tribute, not literally a sacrifice to a god. So it's
quite significant in the fact about like how the relations demanded that
even though there were these obviously sort of problematic elements to it.
Okay, so Rabbi used to do that, okay, and then it says
like this. רש"י Rashi says מקריבין מס ודורון למלך, makrivin mas v'doron
l'melech, like a type of a tribute, a tax, you know, and
a gift, and what's a tribute, it's like an, you know, a
money type of a gift to the king and so on. Right,
but right, but רש"י Rashi anyway, for רש"י Rashi it's not clear
that they would, it doesn't sound like they would use it as
a sacrifice. That would really be amazing if like I mean or
whatever shocking, right, if he would give them something that they then
would turn around, you know, we talk about non-Jews sending their animals
to be brought as קרבנות korbanot in the Temple. Imagine Rabbi sending
a fattened calf that they're going to bring in the Temple of
Zeus. So רש"י Rashi is very careful. רש"י Rashi says no, no,
no, no. It might be in the honor of the holiday, but
you know at least רש"י Rashi did not want to imagine, I
don't know, that they actually used it as a sacrifice. Okay, now
חיסר ארבע ריבבן, chisar arba ribvan, he had to, he expended forty
thousand like, you know, coins, gold coins, שאין מקריבין אותו היום אלא
למחר. she'ein makrivin oto hayom ela l'machar. He said, he agreed to
give a tribute of forty thousand, obviously it's exaggeration, coins, that they
should allow him to give the fattened calf the day after the
holiday, not on the holiday itself, so he shouldn't violate the Rabbinic
prohibition of doing this type of stuff on the holiday. And then
one minute, חיסר ארבע ריבבן chisar arba ribvan and then that was
stage one. Stage two is another forty thousand שאין מקריבין אותו חי
אלא שחוט. she'ein makrivin oto chai ela shachut. He wouldn't have to
give it alive, he could give it slaughtered. Now what's the benefit
of that? Well, if they were going to give it as a
sacrifice, certainly that would be a benefit. Again רש"י Rashi denies that,
but or you know doesn't even, but it also solves the problem
about selling an animal to non-Jews, right? He didn't want to be,
he didn't want to be giving, we didn't talk about giving, but
giving probably would be included, maybe not, I don't know, we talked
about selling or renting. But anyway, okay, he didn't want to be
giving an animal to non-Jews because of this Rabbinic prohibition. So he's
willing to spend these forty thousand dollars or whatever it was, probably
more than forty thousand dollars. Okay, anyway, חיסר ארבע ריבבני chisar arba
ribvani and spent it with that שאין מקריבין אותו כל עיקר. she'ein
makrivin oto kol ikar. He finally managed to give them another forty
thousand that he should be free from this tribute altogether. One minute,
so מאי טעמא? mai ta'ama? Now why did he spend this money
if it was a שור של פטם? shor shel patem? So if
the Rabbinic prohibition of animals to non-Jews doesn't apply to a שור
של פטם, shor shel patem, why was he spending so much money
after he got it to be not on their holiday? He should
have been done. Okay, so מאי טעמא, mai ta'ama, לאו משום דילמא
אתי לאשויי? lav mishum dilma ati l'ashvaye? Isn't it that he felt
that even once it wasn't on the holiday, it was the day
after, he was still violating the Rabbinic prohibition because they could leave
it around and use it for work? So the גמרא Gemara says
ולטעמיך, v'l'ta'amicha, according to your reason, שאין מקריבין אותו היום אלא למחר,
she'ein makrivin oto hayom ela l'machar, מאי טעמא? mai ta'ama? Why did
Rabbi spend the money if that's true? Right, why did Rabbi spend
the money to move it from, you know, from the יום א
yom e to the next day? Now it's a little funny question,
what do you mean? He spent the money to move it from
the יום א yom e to the next day to not violate
doing this stuff on the יום א. yom e. Okay, but the
גמרא Gemara. says, אלא רבי מעקר מלתא בעי. ela Rabbi me'akar milta
ba'ei. Bottom line is Rabbi wanted to stop doing it altogether. וסבר
יעקר ואתי פורסא פורסא. v'savar ye'akar v'ati pursa pursa. I'm going to
do it in stages. So you're right, maybe nothing benefited, you know,
once he got it off of the holiday, maybe he was technically
out of the problem of the שור של פטם, shor shel patem,
of giving them an ox. But bottom line is he wanted to
get out of this altogether. It wasn't because of the Rabbinic prohibition.
So he was doing it in stages. Okay, anyway, so that's why,
but it wasn't because necessarily selling them this fattened animal would have
been a violation. So now the גמרא Gemara says, actually by the
way it's interesting in passing that it makes it sound like included
in the prohibition is also gifts, not just sale and rental. So
now the גמרא says וכי משו ליה ברי ואבדו מלאכה? v'chi mashu
leh bari v'avdu melacha? Are you to... I don't even get your
question. The שור פטם shor patam you say should be a problem
because it's possible to wait for it to maybe lose some of
its extra weight and then you would use it as a work
animal. Is that really true? Is that possible? So אמר רב אשי,
Amar Rav Ashi, yes, אמר ליה זוידא בר תורא Amlei Zvida bar
Tora משוו ליה ועביד חד טרין. mashvu lei veavid al chad trein.
So yes, if you take this ox and זוידא בר תורא, Zvida
bar Tora, actually that was his name. Right, so רש"י Rashi says
that that was his business. His business was that he was into,
you know, oxen and whatever, fattening animals. And he said yes, if
you let this animal, you know, if you wait till it loses
its weight it actually will do the work of two animals. Okay.
Anyway, bottom line, that's the גמרא's question about how בר תורא משוו
ליה. bar Tora mashvu lei. Doesn't בר תורא bar Tora say that
the שור shor should be פטמו משוו ליה, patmu mashvu lei, actually
that's a קשיא. Yeah, right, right, that's how I read it first
and then I went back because of the way you were reading
it. Yeah, but רש"י Rashi does say that זוידא Zvida was פטם
היה, patam haya, that was his business. Right, but if you take
one of these animals, בר תורא, bar Tora, right, so משוו ליה
mashvu lei if you let it wait around then it'll do twice
as much. Anyway, so this is a question of exactly how much
you define the לא פלוג lo pelug category because we have two
תנאים Tannaim that make distinctions. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that makes a
distinction with a broken leg, which is on the one hand it'll
never do work again, on the other hand it's more of a
circumstance, not a category. And בן בתירא Ben Batera who makes a
distinction about horses and he said he's got a whole category that
fundamentally isn't going to do מלאכה. melacha And that leaves the גמרא
asking well what about other parts of distinctions. If we rule like
בן בתירא Ben Batera whatever how about an animal that's being fattened
and before the גמרא talks about just cows in general maybe the
presumption is that it's a context of לשחיטה lishchita and so on,
yes. He gives someone forty thousand dollars rather than a cow. Well,
forty thousand dollars will buy about twenty cows. Right, I think it
was he gave it to them once and then he would not
have to do it from that point on. It wasn't that each
year he would spend that money. He gave that to get out
of the annual obligation. Okay, so let's take a look at the
next משנה. mishna אין מוכרין להם דובים ואריות, Ein mochrin lahem dubim
vaarayot, yeah I get a mention here. Okay, you can't sell to
them since we've been discussing to some degree the issue of כלי
זין klei zayin
now gets to this issue about not exactly things that are used
as weapons but things that are seen as a dangerous thing and
therefore a concern about whether you know they will be as careful
as needed by these things. אין מוכרין להם דובים ואריות, Ein mochrin
lahem dubim vaarayot, you don't sell them bears and lions, וכל דבר
שיש בו נזק
לרבים, vechol davar sheyesh bo nezek larabbim,
anything that could be a source of damage. Now this is interesting,
this is different, this again it's always interesting what it reflects about
our assumptions of non-Jews or what the תנאים's Tannaim assumption. It's one
thing to say look you see that the Romans you know go
and they fight wars and sometimes actually you know they fought wars
against us, you know should we be arming them, right? But you
know but then it's things like but then there's this other stuff
like they suspect them or maybe depending on the circumstances or where
the מנהג minhag is whatever about bestiality. Well here it's just they
suspect them of just not being as responsible citizens. You know if
we had a lion in our house we would be responsible for
it. Of course you remember that the משנה mishna in בבא קמא
Bava Kamma says that you have to kill the lion and the
bear. You can't whatever you know and so so the point is
like yes we are very responsible about those things but basically we
don't own them. Okay, so what are you doing selling it to
the Roman? How did you get it if you don't own it?
Maybe you're doing business in it. You know that they use it
in their stadiums and you know they use it in their whatever
you know they would do this thing. So therefore like these are
too dangerous, nobody should be owning them and therefore don't sell them.
So again I'm not sure if the statement that the Romans are
whatever the גויים goyim are less responsible than we are or it's
just like we ourselves don't own them so why should we be
selling it to them, yes. Are there a lot of Jews in
the bear trade?
Right, so I have no idea what the context would be. Okay,
now, now we finally move to something we're going to get close
to also questions about actually well this is still in the נזק
nezek category. It might sound a little bit like it's the עבודה
זרה but it's still the נזק nezek category. As we continue, אין
בונין עמהם בסילקי, ein bonin imman basilikei, you cannot build with them
a בסילקי, basilikei, right which is like a big like whatever tower
a big building, גרדום אצטדיא ובימה. gardom istadya uveima. גרדום gardom is
like a scaffold, אצטדיא istadya is a stadium and a בימה beima
is also some type of a platform. Now why? So the בסילקי
basilikei is not so clear, but we'll get to that in the
גמרא. The גמרא actually says it doesn't really mean it exactly. But
the stadium is because why do you think you can't build the
stadium for the for the גויים? goyim? Because there'll be gladiator fights
so people will be killed and who are some of the people
that will get killed in the gladiator Jews, okay exactly you know
that's what they did they took the captive you know the people
they captured and they threw them into the stadium or whatever. Okay
so that's number one. I mean the משנה Mishnah the ברייתא braita
says whatever you're allowed to go to the stadium on שבת, you
know though it's obviously very not שבתדיק, Shabbostik, you know everybody whatever
because הצלת נפשות. hatzalas nefashos.
What's the הצלת נפשות? hatzalas nefashos? That after you know I after
like whatever you at there's a certain point, Charlie will know this,
where the where basically the audience votes. Right, it's thumbs up or
thumbs down and if enough people do thumbs up they save him,
right? They don't kill the guy. Is that right? Anyway, so you
know you could go there to help save the people. Anyway, so
that's stadiums. Okay. The גרדום Gardom and the בימה, Bima, the גרדום
Gardom is presumably, רש״י Rashi says it's one way, it might be
the other way, it doesn't matter, one of these is like the
platform where the judges sit and the other is like the scaffold
where they actually do the hanging or they throw the person off
the scaffold and they do the executions. So enough Jews were executed
by the Romans and the Roman court that anything that is helping
them
build their structures for where they're going to either their courthouses or
where they're actually going to do their executions, we cannot be participating
in that. רש״י Rashi claims that maybe the בסיליקי Basilike is also
a type of a structure that was used as a courthouse. So
yeah, the way he translates the second one here, here they say
tribunal, גרדום. Gardom. גרדום Gardom is tribunal? That's what he says. That's
interesting. Tribunal? What do you mean a tribunal? גרדום Gardom is a
building. You mean some building for a tribunal or was tribunal the
name of a building? I thought a tribunal was a three-person, a
three-body, whatever. Anyway, שטיינזלץ Steinsaltz says it's from a Latin word that
originally meant steps and it was the steps up leading up to
where the judge sat. Okay, so it's where the judge sits and
the בימה Bima similarly, or the בימה Bima
might be the platform where the judges would sit. We're assuming that
these are also from the מפורשים, Meforshim, I mean these, even if
this was a civil court you could, yeah, right,
that's exactly that. If they had a distinction about civil buildings and
criminal ones, probably it would not be a problem. אבל בונים עמהם
בימוסיות, Aval bonim imom bimosiot,
you can build with them בימוסיות. bimosiot. I'm going to get back
to that word in a second. Some have the גרסא דימוסיות, girsa
dimosiot, ובית מרחצאות u-beit merchatzaot and bathhouses. Okay, because what's the problem
with a bathhouse? Because as we know, the famous משנה about the
idol of Aphrodite in the bathhouse, but okay, a bathhouse is still
a bathhouse, fundamentally it's not about idols. הגיע לכיפה שמעמידין בה עבודה
זרה, Higia le-kipa she-ma'amidim bo avoda zara,
when you get to the certain like the archway, or whatever the,
what they called the nape? The niche. Niche, not niche, but something
else, and nave? The nave. The nave. I think whatever it is,
what do I know about these terms? Anyway, what? A nave is
something different. Of a person, a knave, right? That's with a K.
Okay. Anyway, whatever it is, this type of a niche, you see
these like insets into the wall, anyway, the place where they would
put the idol. In that case, אסור לבנות, assur livnot, I can't
help you with that. שטיינזלץ Steinsaltz has a picture. Oh, there you
go. שטיינזלץ. Steinsaltz. Exactly that. Okay. You see them today in the
Bronx. Okay. Now what is this בימוסיות? bimosiot? So רש״י Rashi says
that this is a, if you look at רש״י, Rashi, okay, רש״י
Rashi says, רש״י, Rashi, בימוסיות גרסינן, bimosiot garsinan, two lines down in
the wide lines, בנין שאינו לצורך עבודת כוכבים, binyan she-eino letzorach avodat
kochavim, you don't really use it for idolatry. What do you mean,
so what do you use it for? He says, ומפרש גם בפרק
רבי ישמעאל וקורין לו אלטר דקתני בימוסיות שלא עובדי כוכבים מותר. u-mefarash
gam beperek Rabi Yishmael ve-korin lo Alter de-ktani bimosiot she-lo ovdei kochavim
mutar. ומאי בימוס? U-mai Bimos? בימה של אבן אחת, Bima shel even
achat, it was one stone, ומקריב זבחים u-makriv zvachim and you offer
sacrifices on it. דהוי תשמיש דעבודה זרה ולאו אפי עבודה זרה, De-havei
tashmish d'avoda zara u-le-afi avoda zara, two degrees removed. Like what? That
would be worse! Like a תשמיש דעבודה זרה tashmish d'avoda zara using
an altar to bring sacrifices. So it sounds like רש״י Rashi is
saying that since I'm not actually doing somehow the act with the
altar, I'm doing the act with the animal and it's just on
the altar, it's like two degrees removed. תוספות of course says this
is absolutely crazy, this makes no sense, of course this is a
תשמיש דעבודה זרה, tashmish d'avoda zara, you're directly using this altar in
an act of הקרבה hakrava and תוספות says even if technically it
was two degrees removed, you think we would let a Jew build
an altar that they're going to bring עבודה זרה on? We're not
going to go by technical formalities here. This is way too close
to עבודה זרה. So תוספות says the גרסא girsa is not בימוסיות
bimosiot it's דימוסיות dimosiot and a דימוסיות dimosiot is a type of
a bathhouse, okay, it's sort of like the מרחצאות. merchatzaot. All right?
So how does what does רש״י Rashi do with the fact that
you can't even build that little niche over there? Rashi would say
it's directly connected to the idol, this he would say is used
in a, it's bizarre how you're splitting that hair, which is what
תוספות asks. אמר רב חנא בר רב חסדא ואמרי לה אמר רב
חנן בר רבא אמר רב, Amar Rav Chana bar Rav Chisda ve-amrei
lah Amar Rav Chanan bar Rava Amar Rav, חיה גסה הרי היא
כבהמה דקה לפירכוס. chaya gasa harei hi ke-behema daka le-pirchus. There's a
הלכה that when you שוחט shecht an animal, you in order to
see that it was not dying, it has to thrash a little
bit after you שוחט shecht it to show that it had a
good life force in it. So if it is a large animal
like a cow, it's enough that it just stretches out its arms.
But if it's a small animal like a sheep, it has to
stretch out and pull back, okay, that's called פירכוס. pirchus. Okay. So
what about if you שוחט shecht a חיה גסה? chaya gasa? What
if you שוחט shecht like a deer? Is a deer like a
cow and it's enough to stretch out its arms or is it
like a sheep that has to stretch out and pull back? So
he says חיה גסה הרי היא כבהמה דקה לפירכוס, chaya gasa harei
hi ke-behema daka le-pirchus, for the need of tremors, okay, after you
שוחט shecht for it to be a כשר שחיטה kosher shechita you
have to see it stretch out its arms and pull them back.
Okay. אבל לא למכירה, Aval lo l'mechira, but when it comes to
the הלכות halachas of selling to non-Jews, it's in the category of
large animals not small animals. Small animals you remember is based on
מנהג, minhag, this is in the large animal category and it's totally
forbidden to sell. Why? What were we worried? Well, we're going to
discuss that. What מלאכה melacha, do you do with your deer? Exactly.
So we're going to see about that in a minute. Okay. So,
ואני אומר, ve-ani omer, and I say. say אף למכירה, af le-michira,
now it's like a small animal even for selling. מקום שנהגו למכור
מוכרים שלא נהגו אין מקום Makom she-nahagu limkor mochrim she-lo linhagu ein
makom at all based on the מנהג. minhag. תנן, Tenan, now let's
try to prove this. אין מוכרים דובים ואריות ולא כל דבר שיש
בו נזק לרבים. Ein mochrim dubim va'arayot velo kol davar she-yesh bo
nezek larabbim. You can't sell them these lions and bears and anything
that is a hazard to the masses. טעמא דאיכא נזק לרבים, Ta'ama
de-ika nezek larabbim, the reason is because it's a hazard. הא ליכא
נזק לרבים, Ha leika nezek larabbim, if it were something like a
lion or a bear that was not a dangerous animal, שרי, shari,
you'd be permitted. So something that's like a lion and bear not
a dangerous animal is a חיה, chaya, a חיה גסה, chaya gassa,
a large non-domesticated animal, as long as it's not dangerous it would
be permissible. So this seems that normal חיה chaya is permissible to
sell for the obvious reason that Michael says, who's doing work with
a חיה? chaya? So אמר רבה בר עולא, Amar Rabba bar Ulla,
so doesn't that prove the setup permissible? בארי שבור. Be-ari shavur. No,
the lion's got a broken leg, like Rabbi Yehuda allows with broken
legs, the lion's got a broken leg and that's why if it
weren't a lion it would be permitted. But otherwise, באליבא דרבי יהודה,
ba-aliba de-Rabbi Yehuda, which is a little bit absurd because really with
or without a broken leg, these animals are not doing מלאכה, melacha,
which is what Rav Ashi says. רב אשי אמר, Rav Ashi amar,
סתם ארי שבור הוא אצל מלאכה. stam ari shavur hu etzel melacha.
No, a lion is like it's got a broken leg. Nobody uses
a lion for work, which means what he's saying is that maybe
you're right, maybe 90% of חיות chayot can't do work and those
animals are not included in the prohibition. But if you find a
חיה גסה chaya gassa that would be used in a work context,
that would be included. So that's his argument. מיתיבי, Meitivi, I'll ask
you, כשם שאין מוכרים בהמה גסה כך אין מוכרים חיה גסה. keshem
she-ein mochrim behema gassa kach ein mochrim chaya gassa. The Baraita is
explicit, the Tosefta. The same way you don't sell them a large
בהמה, you don't sell them a large חיה. chaya. ואפילו במקום שמוכרים
בהמה דקה חיה גסה אין מוכרים. ve-afilu be-makom she-mochrim behema daka chaya
gassa ein mochrim. The Baraita says you don't sell a חיה גסה,
chaya gassa, it's explicit, you don't. תיובתא דרב חנא בר רבא תיובתא.
Tiyuvta de-Rav Chana bar Rabba tiyuvta. That completely rejects this argument and
that shows that you are forbidden to sell, which is strange because
again, it's a type of a לאו פלוג. lo pelug. It's very
strange. רבינא רמי מתניתין אברייתא ומשני. Ravina rami matnitin a-baraita u-meshani. He
showed a contradiction between the Mishnah and the Baraita and he answered.
תנן אין מוכרים דובים ואריות ולא כל דבר שיש בו נזק לרבים.
Tenan ein mochrim dubim va'arayot velo kol davar she-yesh bo nezek larabbim.
You don't sell them bears and lions or anything that's dangerous. טעמא
דאיכא נזק, Ta'ama de-ika nezek, only because it's dangerous. הא ליכא נזק
מוכרים. Ha leika nezek mochrim. If it wouldn't be dangerous you could,
so presumably you can sell a חיה גסה. chaya gassa. ורמינהי, U-reminhi,
I'll ask you, we got a Baraita, כשם שאין מוכרים בהמה גסה
כך אין מוכרים חיה גסה. keshem she-ein mochrim behema gassa kach ein
mochrim chaya gassa. ואפילו במקום שמוכרים בהמה דקה חיה גסה אין מוכרים.
ve-afilu be-makom she-mochrim behema daka chaya gassa ein mochrim. The Baraita says
you don't sell a חיה גסה, chaya gassa, but the implication of
our Mishnah is you do sell a חיה גסה. chaya gassa. ומשני
בארי שבור ובאליבא דרבי יהודה. u-meshani be-ari shavur u-ve-aliba de-Rabbi Yehuda. No,
our Mishnah only allows it by a lion with a broken leg,
but if it was another חיה גסה chaya gassa it would be
forbidden. רב אשי אמר, Rav Ashi amar, סתם ארי שבור הוא אצל
מלאכה. stam ari shavur hu etzel melacha. Really, it's not just that
it has a broken leg, it's because it's a lion. If you've
got a חיה גסה chaya gassa that is unusable for מלאכה, it
would not be included. But if you have a חיה גסה chaya
gassa that's usable, that would be included in the prohibition. I don't
know what חיה גסה chaya gassa that would be. So finally it's
not completely excluded, if a particular חיה גסה chaya gassa type of
lion type of animal is not ראוי למלאכה, ra'ui le-melacha, it's excluded.
But the whole category is not excluded. מתקיף לה רב נחמן, Matkif
lah Rav Nachman, מאן דאמר לן דארי חיה גסה הוא? man de-amar
lan de-ari chaya gassa hu? So Rav Nachman just threw in like
a monkey wrench. What makes you think that a lion is a
large animal? דילמא חיה דקה היא? dilma chaya daka hi? Maybe it's
a small animal. What? I've no idea what he's talking about. Maybe
he means like what are those things, those like small cats that
are sort of bobcats or cougars or whatever? So maybe he's including
that in the word of ארי. ari. Anyway, Rav Ashi now going
back, רב אשי דייק מתניתין ומוסיף תיובתא. Rav Ashi dayek matnitin u-mosif
tiyuvta. Rav Ashi sort of does the same thing by just reading
the Mishnah closely and then he asks his question. תנן אין מוכרים
דובים ואריות ולא כל דבר שיש בו נזק לרבים. Tenan ein mochrim
dubim va'arayot velo kol davar she-yesh bo nezek larabbim. טעמא דאיכא נזק,
Ta'ama de-ika nezek, you only can't sell dangerous animals. הא ליכא נזק
מוכרים, Ha leika nezek mochrim, otherwise you could sell. וטעמא ארי, ve-ta'ama
ari, and it's only a lion. So now he incorporates what in
the previous discussion was an answer, he incorporates this as an assumption.
The only thing you can't sell them is a lion. The only
reason you would be able to sell it if it weren't dangerous
is because it's a lion. דסתם ארי שבור הוא אצל מלאכה, de-stam
ari shavur hu etzel melacha, because a lion can't do work. And
that's why it would be allowed were it not dangerous. אבל מידי
אחריני, aval midi achrini, but if it was another חיה גסה chaya
gassa that could be used in work דעביד מלאכה, da-avid melacha, לא,
that could be used in work it would be forbidden. Again, you
have to find what חיה גסה chaya gassa that is. But at
least in principle, we are not excluding the whole category of חיה
גסה. chaya gassa. The types of חיה גסה chaya gassa that don't
do work, אי נמי, ee nami, those are excluded. But a חיה
גסה chaya gassa that could do work would not be excluded. תיובתא
דרב חנא בר רבא תיובתא. Tiyuvta de-Rav Chana bar Rabba tiyuvta. That
completely rejects Rav Chana bar Rabba. I'm not taking questions yet because
I want to get a little further. וחיה גסה מי עבדי מלאכה?
Ve-chaya gassa mi avdi melacha? So finally the Gemara asks itself, you've
proved it to me three different ways that חיה גסה chaya gassa
is included in the prohibition, assuming that it could do work. What
type of work are you going to do with a חיה גסה?
chaya gassa? מאי מלאכה עבדי? Mai melacha avdi? So the Gemara says
אמר אביי אמר לי מר יהודה דבי מר יוחני, Amar Abaye amar
li Mar Yehuda de-vei Mar Yochnai, מר יהודה Mar Yehuda said in
the house of מר יוחני, Mar Yochnai, טוחני ריחיים בערודי. tochni rei-chaim
b'arodei. They use this ערוד arode by ערודי. arodey. They use this
ערוד arode which is like what is it like a wild donkey,
they use it to turn the millstone. So yeah, not lions, not
bears, not deer, but there are some wild animals that they capture
them and they actually do employ them for work. And those would
be forbidden. Elephants. Elephants, oh that's a good one. Okay. אמר רב
זירא כי הוינא בי רב יהודה, Amar Rav Zeira ki havina bei
Rav Yehuda, when I was in the house of רב יהודה, Rav
Yehuda, אמר ליה, amar lei, סמירו מינאי הא מילתא. smiru minai ha
milta. I want you to learn from me the following thing I'm
going to teach this to you, pay attention. דמגברא רבא שמיעא לי.
de-migavra raba shmia li. I heard this from a great authority. ולא
ידענא, ve-lo yadna, I don't know, said רב יהודה, Rav Yehuda, this
is saying in the name of רב יהודה Rav Yehuda that רב
יהודה Rav Yehuda said this to the students in his ישיבה. Yeshiva.
רב זירא Rav Zeira said, in the ישיבה Yeshiva of רב יהודה,
Rav Yehuda, here's what he said to his students. He said רב
יהודה Rav Yehuda was a student of רב Rav and שמואל. Shmuel.
So רב יהודה Rav Yehuda got up in his ישיבה Yeshiva and
said, students, pay attention. I want you to hear this really important
teaching I got it from a great authority. I don't remember אי
מרב אי משמואל ei me-Rav ei mi-Shmuel whether I got it from
רב Rav or שמואל, Shmuel, but pay attention. Here's the teaching: חיה
גסה הרי היא כבהמה דקה לפרכוס. chaya gassa harei hi ke-behema daka
le-pirchus. Going back to the point which was not our point. Okay,
a large חיה chaya is like a small animal for the לפרכוס
le-pirchus for the tremor. And it's only כשר kosher after you שחט-ed
shecht it if it stretches its arm out and back in. That's
the teaching. Remember that. So then says רב זירא, Rav Zeira, כי
אתאי לקורקוניא ki atai le-Kurkonya wherever that is, when I came to
this place, אשכחתיה לרב חייא בר אשי דיתיב וקאמר ashkachtei le-Rav Chiya
bar Ashi de-yasiv ve-ka-amar I found רב חייא בר אשי Rav Chiya
bar Ashi and he was sitting and saying משמיה דשמואל mishmeih de-Shmuel
in the name of שמואל, Shmuel, חיה גסה הרי היא כבהמה דקה
לפרכוס chaya gassa harei hi ke-behema daka le-pirchus this teaching. אמינא, Amina,
I said, שמע מינה משמיה דשמואל מרה. shma mina mishmeih de-Shmuel mara.
Ah, now I can go back and tell רב יהודה Rav Yehuda
that this teaching comes from שמואל. Shmuel. He didn't know if it
came from רב Rav or שמואל. Shmuel. כי אתאי לסורא ki atai
le-Sura but then I came to סורא, Sura, ואשכחתיה לרבה בר ירמיה
דיתיב וקאמר לה משמיה דרב. ve-ashkachtei le-Rabba bar Yirmeya de-yasiv ve-ka-amar lah
mishmeih de-Rav. And then I heard רבה בר ירמיה Rabba bar Yirmeya
saying in the name of רב, Rav, חיה גסה הרי היא כבהמה
דקה לפרכוס. chaya gassa harei hi ke-behema daka le-pirchus. So now I
hear that it's a transition. רב יהודה Rav Yehuda didn't know did
he get it from רב Rav or שמואל. Shmuel. Now I've heard
one רב Rav teach it in the name of שמואל, Shmuel, another
רב Rav teach it in the name of רב. Rav. אמינא שמע
מינה איתמר משמיה דרב ואיתמר משמיה דשמואל. Amina shma mina itmar mishmeih
de-Rav ve-itmar mishmeih de-Shmuel. Ah, now I get why רב יהודה Rav
Yehuda couldn't remember because it was both a teaching of רב Rav
and a teaching of שמואל. Shmuel. Wait, the story isn't over. כי
סליקת להתם ki silikas le-hasam when I finally went to ארץ ישראל,
Eretz Yisrael, אשכחתיה לרב אסי דיתיב וקאמר, ashkachtei le-Rav Assi de-yasiv ve-ka-amar,
I found רב אסי Rav Assi and he was sitting and saying,
אמר רב חמא בר גוריא משמיה דרב. amar Rav Chama bar Guria
mishmeih de-Rav. So rather than a teaching of רב יהודה Rav Yehuda
in the name of רב, Rav, this was saying a teaching of
רב חמא בר גוריא Rav Chama bar Guria in the name of
רב. Rav. חיה גסה הרי היא כבהמה דקה לפרכוס. chaya gassa harei
hi ke-behema daka le-pirchus. Okay, so now we know it came from
רב Rav and we know it came from שמואל. Shmuel. But now
we got question number two. Was it רב Rav through רב יהודה
Rav Yehuda or was it רב Rav through רב חמא בר גוריא?
Rav Chama bar Guria? I don't know why it can't be both,
maybe they both heard it from רב. Rav. But anyway אמינא ליה,
amina lei, I said, ולא סבר ליה מר דמאן מרה דשמעתא רבה
בר ירמיה? ve-lo savar lei mar de-man mara de-shmata Rabba bar Yirmeya?
Don't you hold that the master of this teaching is רבה בר
ירמיה? Rabba bar Yirmeya? Because רבה בר ירמיה Rabba bar Yirmeya was
the one who said it. Right, in the name of רב. Rav.
Excuse me, forget also רב יהודה. Rav Yehuda. I've heard this from
רבה בר ירמיה Rabba bar Yirmeya in the name of רב, Rav,
not from רב חמא בר גוריא Rav Chama bar Guria in the
name of רב. Rav. So wasn't this tradition passed down through רבה
בר ירמיה? Rabba bar Yirmeya? אמר לי amar li he said back
to me, פסיא אוכמא pasiya uchma you black vessel. That does not
sound like a compliment, but רש״י Rashi says it is because it
means you are so studious that you know you don't take care
of your clothes and your walls get black and whatever. So somehow
it's a compliment. Okay, so anyway מינאי ומינך תסתיים שמעתא. minai u-minach
tistayem shmata. This is a very famous, this is a good rabbinic
line. מינאי ומינך תסתיים שמעתא. minai u-minach tistayem shmata. From our two
teachings together we can figure out what's going on here. From me
and from you we will conclude this teaching, we'll figure out who
the authority is. איתמר נמי אמר רב זירא אמר רב אסי אמר
רבה בר ירמיה אמר רב חמא בר גוריא אמר רב. itmar nami
amar Rav Zeira amar Rav Assi amar Rabba bar Yirmeya amar Rav
Chama bar Guria amar Rav. So what does that mean? We're both
right. How are we both right? It was taught also says רב
זירא, Rav Zeira, says רב אסי, Rav Assi, says רבה בר ירמיה,
Rabba bar Yirmeya, says רב חמא בר גוריא, Rav Chama bar Guria,
says רב. Rav. So was it רבה בר ירמיה Rabba bar Yirmeya
in the name of רב Rav or was it רב חמא בר
גוריא Rav Chama bar Guria in the name of רב? Rav? And
the answer was yes, it was רבה בר ירמיה Rabba bar Yirmeya
in the name of רב חמא בר גוריא Rav Chama bar Guria
in the name of רב. Rav. חיה גסה הרי היא כבהמה דקה
לפרכוס. chaya gassa harei hi ke-behema daka le-pirchus. Ah, so we resolved
it. It was both רב Rav and שמואל, Shmuel, both רב בר
חמא Rav bar Chama and רבה בר ירמיה, Rabba bar Yirmeya, or
wherever it was, and רב חמא בר גוריא. Rav Chama bar Guria.
It was all of them, they all had that tradition. Okay, and
now you know if you שחט shecht a deer it has to
do פרכוס pirchus like a sheep. Okay, we'll pick up from this.